בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we are continuing in פרק חלק, Perek Chelek,
דף קג, Daf Kuf Gimmel, 103. We're in the middle of the
three evil kings: ירבעם, Yerovam, אחאב, Achav, and מנשה. Menashe. We dealt
with ירבעם, Yerovam, who split the kingdom, although the prophet told him
to, where that he would. Anyway, he made the two golden calves,
so he also led all the people to idolatry, and as we
pointed out, all the future kings of Israel that did evil were
always attributed after ירבעם. Yerovam. They continued to do evil like ירבעם.
Yerovam. And now we're up to אחאב, Achav, who was one of
the great, one of the terrible kings. He's the one with איזבל,
Izevel, with dealing with the vineyard, with doing all this murder and
idolatry and so on. Okay, so we pick up when the, but
the גמרא Gemara says, you know, he had a very long reign
and that was because he, at least through the מדרש Midrash eyes,
he protected the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. He treasured the ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
and then it had a, right, so then it said, okay, oh,
it also that he was very generous with his money, that while
his wife איזבל Izevel was giving all this money to עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, he was giving the money to support
תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei Chachamim. Maybe. Right, exactly. Okay, now,
ויצא. Vayetze. So now we pick up about ten lines from the
bottom, right where there's a circle, quoting the פסוק, Pasuk, continuing in
this part where God is sort of speaking to the spirits that
are in front of him: Who is going to go seduce אחאב?
Achav? And then he's going to go fall in this battle. ויצא
הרוח ויעמד לפני ה׳, Vayetze haruach vayaamod lifnei Hashem, and so one
of the spirits came and stood before God. ויאמר אני אפתנו, Vayomar
ani apatenu, I will seduce him. ויאמר ה׳ אליו במה, Vayomer Hashem
elav bameh, how? ויאמר אצא והייתי רוח שקר בפי כל נביאיו, Vayomer
etze vehayiti ruach sheker befi kol nevi'av,
I will be a false spirit, a false like spirit in all
of the, in all of the false prophets, and they'll all prophesy
that whatever, he should go to war, he'll go to war and
he'll fall in battle. Okay, ויאמר תפתה, Vayomer tepateh,
God says, go seduce him. גם תוכל, Gam tuchal, and you should
be successful. צא ועשה כן, Tze vaaseh ken, do, go and do
and do so and so on. מאי רוח? Mai ruach? What was
this רוח? ruach? אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabi Yochanan: רוחו של נבות
היזרעאלי. rucho shel Nabot haYizre'eli.
So the, right, the spirit of נבות היזרעאלי, Nabot haYizre'eli, the guy
he, what, he stole the, what do you call it from, the
vineyard from and so on. So now he's getting his comeuppance, and
maybe it's also this idea, you know, we always, we were discussing
in general, since so much about this is עולם הבא Olam HaBa
and we said the גמרא's Gemara עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, at least
in this context, is basically the world after the Messianic period, you
know, but also there's this עולם הבא Olam HaBa about where the,
you know, which is in fewer sources or whatever, but it becomes
dominant for us, you know, where the, where the soul goes after
the, you know, after death. So here, you know, here's this idea,
right, it's a disembodied soul of this נבות היזרעאלי, Nabot haYizre'eli, and
he is going to find, get his justice. Okay, מאי צא? Mai
tze? What does it mean go out? You didn't have to say
צא, tze, just said, you know, go be successful. אמר רבינא: Amar
Ravina: צא ממחיצתי, Tze mimichitzati,
fine, it's a job you have to do, but get out, I
don't want you here anymore with me. שכן כתיב: Sheken ketiv: דובר
שקרים לא יכון לנגד עיני, dover shekarim lo yikon leneged einai, you
know, you're going to go ahead and you're going to speak falsehood.
I don't know, maybe there was a way to have done it
without lying, and so and sometimes some people, it's a dirty job,
it's got to get done, but once you're doing it, I don't
want you here with me anymore.
But the Torah's conception of Satan is not like some something that
lies, it's just something that's enticing.
Right, exactly, that's a good point, right, the פיתוי, pitu'i, which is
what God was asking, is not the same as to lie. Exactly.
Okay,
אמר פפא: Amar Papa: היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu de'amrei inshi, that's what
people say. דפרע קינא מחריב ביתיה, Dipara kinei machriv beiteh, the one
who, who like, who finds justice for his zealotry or for his
jealousy ultimately destroys your home. You know, you might get satisfaction and
wind up, you know, exacting, what?
His own home.
His own home. You might get satisfaction from, oh, you finally were
able to act on all those jealous feelings and take vengeance, but
in the end it'll be very destructive for yourself. Okay, ויעש אחאב
את האשרה, Vayaas Achav et ha'asheirah, okay, and אחאב Achav made the
אשרה, asheira, okay, and אחאב Achav made the, right, this tree or
whatever of idol worship. ויוסף אחאב לעשות להכעיס את ה׳ אלהי ישראל
מכל מלכי ישראל, Vayosef Achav laasot lehachis et Hashem elokei Yisrael mikol
malchei Yisrael,
he did more to anger God than all of the kings of
Israel אשר היו לפניו Asher hayu lefanav that were before him. אמר
רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabi Yochanan:
so what did he do really to like make a point of
how big of a רשע rasha he was? שכתב על דלתות שמרון,
Shekatav al daltot Shomron, he wrote on the doors of שמרון: Shomron:
אחאב כפר באלהי ישראל, Achav kafar be'elokei Yisrael, אחאב, Achav, he
made, he made it like into a philosophy: I have rejected the
God of Israel. ולפיכך אין לו חלק לעולם הבא. Ulefichach ein lo
chelek le'olam haba. באלהי ישראל Be'elokei Yisrael and therefore he has no
portion with the God of Israel, presumably he wrote that. What? No,
no, no, I think the idea is he wrote it. I don't
want anything to do with you. I'm rejecting you, I don't want
anything to do with you. Okay, ויבקש את אחזיהו וילכדהו והוא מתחבא
בשמרון, Vayevakesh et Achazyahu vayilkeduhu vehu mitchabe beShomron,
and they searched out אחזיהו Achazyahu and they sort of and they
seized him and he was hiding in שמרון. Shomron. So now this
is about a certain king אחזיהו, Achazyahu, but it's bizarre the גמרא
Gemara just quotes this and based on what the גמרא... Gemara... I
was going to say later, it seems that the גמרא Gemara is
reading this verse to be about about אחאב. Achav. So I don't
know if your footnotes helps you with that, but אמר רבי לוי
שהיה קודר אזכרות Amar Rabi Levi shehayah koder azkarot that what he
would do is he would take a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, he
would cut out God's names from the ספר תורה Sefer Torah וכותב
עבודת כוכבים תחתיהן, vekotev avodat kokhavim tachtehen, or he'd scrape out God's
names, I guess if you cut it out you need a new
piece of parchment. Anyway and then he'd write the name of עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. So he had the whole ספר תורה Sefer Torah
but he took out השם Hashem and it said I don't know
בעל Baal or אשרה Asherah or whatever. Again, I don't know how
it's reading this to be about אחאב, Achav, but it seems later
that the גמרא Gemara is this we're not just quoting a random
פסוק pasuk about about this אחזיהו, Achazyahu, we're in the end identifying
it with אחאב. Achav. Do your footnotes help you with that at
all? He yielded. Basically. Oh, okay. Anyway maybe it's just saying it
about אחזיהו, Achazyahu, but we're going to say the same thing about
אחאב Achav anyway. All right, moving on.
Okay, מנשה, Menashe, now back now to the third king, מנשה. Menashe.
We're done with אחאב. Achav.
I thought though there's a פסוק pasuk הראית כי נכנע אחאב לפני?
Haraita ki nikhna Achav lifnai? Yeah, יען אשר נכנע אחאב מפני, Yaan
asher nikhna Achav mipanai, יען כי נכנע מפני לא אביא הרעה בימיו.
Yaan ki nikhna mipanai lo avia hara'ah beyamav. That that was that
was what David was asking.
So we're going to see this discussion about מנשה. Menashe. Interestingly, I
think I misled you before, David, I because I was conflating מנשה
Menashe and אחאב. Achav. We're we don't see it by אחאב. Achav.
And I think the assumption is is that he showed a moment
of humility and he was extended given some, you know, extension or
whatever, but it was not true תשובה. teshuvah. I think that's the
assumption.
Didn't חז"ל Chazal say that who asked the king of Israel to
give him stripes every day?
Yeah, they would say that's אחאב Achav also.
And then he did total תשובה teshuvah and he, you know, he
turned around all his, I thought that was אחאב. Achav.
Do we say that by אחאב? Achav?
I thought he was the one that they said that he used
to be get מלקות malkus from the king. That's what I.
You guys, yeah, you could be right. I don't know why it's
not being integrated into this גמרא Gemara here. Charlie?
There's very
the reference is to דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim and there's nothing that
would seem.
Yeah, but they I think you guys might be referring to a
certain אגדתא, Agadta, right? Yeah, so could be that there's an אגדתא
Agadta approach that's in conflict with this גמרא, Gemara, you know, but
yeah.
The successor of אחזיהו Achazyahu was
his mother, אחאב's Achav mother.
No, אחזיהו's Achazyahu
mother.
Oh, אחזיהו Achazyahu was succeeded by his mother.
His mother, yeah.
Okay. All right, moving on. Right, but he was not part of
the whole אחאב Achav thing. Yeah, I don't know why it's I
don't yeah, it's different. Right, I know. So I don't know why
it's bringing it in.
Maybe they just compared.
Yeah, okay. So anyway moving on. I don't know. You guys are
asking good questions. I don't know about אחאב, Achav, but maybe it's
just conflicting, you know, approach. All right. So now but we are
going to discuss it by מנשה. Menashe.
You know what? You guys can do some research, whatever. Ask Rabbi
Google, maybe he'll have an answer. All right, so anyway, okay. Now,
מנשה, Menashe, moving on to מנשה. Menashe. So now we first do
a play on his name, like the significance of his name. שנשייה,
Shenashyah, he forgot God. דבר אחר, Davar acher, מנשה, Menashe, שהנשיא את
ישראל לאביהם שבשמים, shehishia et Yisrael l'avihen shebashamayim, he caused Israel to
be forgotten by God, or he made or he made Israel forget
God. ומנלן דלא אתי לעלמא דאתי, Umanlan d'lo ati l'alma d'ati, how
do you know he doesn't come to the world to come? דכתיב,
Dechtiv, בן שתים עשרה שנה מנשה במלכו וחמשים וחמש שנה מלך בירושלים,
ben shtem esreh shanah Menashe bemolcho vachamishim vechamesh shanah malach b'Yerushalayim, he
was a very he reigned for a very long period of time,
fifty-five years. Okay. ויעש אשרה כאשר עשה אחאב מלך ישראל, Vaya'as Asherah
ka'asher asah Achav melech Yisrael, מה אחאב אין לו חלק לעולם הבא
אף מנשה אין לו חלק לעולם הבא, mah Achav ein lo chelek
l'olam haba af Menashe ein lo chelek l'olam haba, we do by
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. רבי יהודה אומר מנשה יש לו חלק לעולם
הבא, Rabbi Yehuda omer Menashe yesh lo chelek l'olam haba, שנאמר, shenemar,
ויתפלל מנשה אל ה' ויעתר לו האלהים, vayitpallel Menashe el Hashem vay'ater
lo HaElohim, and
מנשה Menashe prayed to God and God was sort of responded to
him, was importuned by him and therefore and therefore that indicates that
at least Rabbi Yehuda is reading that מנשה Menashe in contrast to
אחאב Achav did real תשובה. teshuvah. אמר רבי יוחנן ושניהם מקרא אחד
דרשו, Amar Rabi Yochanan ushneihem mikra echad darshu, they both are interpreting
one verse. שנאמר, Shenemar, ונתתים לזעוה לכל ממלכות הארץ, unatatim l'za'avah l'chol
mamlechot ha'aretz,
I will make them for a like the people the people for
trembling for all the kingdoms of the earth, בגלל מנשה בן יחזקיהו,
biglal Menashe ben Yechizkiyahu, because of מנשה Menashe the son of יחזקיהו,
Yechizkiyahu, that's why there's going to be you know the people there's
going to be this terrible downfall. So what does that mean? Sounds
like he was evil, right? So מר סבר mar savar בגלל מנשה
שעשה תשובה ואינהו לא עביד, biglal Menashe she'asah teshuvah v'inhu lo avid,
no,
because he actually he you know he made it obvious that it
was possible to be really wicked and do תשובה teshuvah and therefore
that in a way indirectly brings you know brings judgment upon the
people.
ומר סבר, Umar savar, and the other said which is more the
פשט, peshat, בגלל מנשה דלא עביד, biglal Menashe d'lo avid, because no,
because of the evil of מנשה Menashe and the evil that he
did and now that's going the people are going to pay for
it. I mean the people followed his way and now everybody's going
to pay for it. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Yochanan, top of
קג עמוד א, kuf gimmel amud aleph, כל האומר מנשה אין לו
חלק לעולם הבא מרפה ידיהם של בעלי תשובה. kol ha'omer Menashe ein
lo chelek l'olam haba merappe yedeihen shel ba'alei teshuvah. He's not saying
it's wrong, right? This is really I love this point because it's
like it's a question of like like which version of the story
do you want to tell, right? If you there you could read
the verses either way, if you're choosing to want to say oh
he was so wicked and terrible and just focus on that and
even after he did תשובה teshuvah did it make a difference, then
that is not a helpful religious message.
Okay. So דהני תנא, dehanei tanna, okay, what about אחר?
Acher? I mean like you know the גמרא Gemara really comes down
hard on that and says like you know even חוץ מאחר chutz
m'Acher no matter what he does like...
yeah, that's a good point. That's a good point too. למה אחר
*lema achar*. Like we tell those stories about אחר *Achar*, which is
like, but there, there's not a basis to say that he did
תשובה teshuva *teshuva*. I mean, you're right. There are people who didn't
do תשובה teshuvah *teshuva*. He's not saying say somebody did תשובה *teshuva*
when he didn't, and then, you know, but he's saying like if
you, if there's a way to say he did תשובה *teshuva*, if
that's a legitimate version here, you should be adopting that version rather
than the other one. Yes.
So the the idea that מנשה menashe. *Menashe* did תשובה *teshuva* is
found in דברי הימים *Divrei Hayamim*, that is missing from ספר מלכים
*Sefer Melachim*.
That is correct.
So then have people written about a potential difference in attitudes in
those two books?
Yes, yes, yes. תני תנא קמיה דרבי יוחנן *Tani tanna kamei d'Rabbi
Yochanan*, because a תנא *tanna* taught in front of Rabbi Yochanan: מנשה
Menashe עשה תשובה שלושים ושלוש שנים *Menashe asa teshuva shloshim v'shalosh shanim*.
For thirty two... for thirty three years he actually was on the
good path. He was on the good path longer than he was
on the bad path, right? Because he was a king for fifty
five years. דכתיב d'chtiv בן שתים עשרה שנה מנשה Menashe במלכו וחמשים
וחמש שנה מלך בירושלים *Dichtiv ben shtaim esre shana Menashe b'molcho v'chamishim
v'chamesh shana malach b'Yerushalayim*. He was king for fifty five years. ויעש
הרע vayaas hara, ככל אשר עשו אחאב Achav מלך ישראל *Vaya'as hara
kechol asher asu Achav melech Yisrael*. And then it describes evil like
like אחאב *Achav*. כמה מלך אחאב *Kama malach Achav*? Asking the תנא
*tanna*. But אחאב *Achav* was king only twenty two years. So מנשה
Menashe. כמה מלך *Menashe kama malach*? How long was he? חמישים וחמש
*Chamishim v'chamesh*. Fifty five. דמי ליה עשרים ושתים *Dami lei esrim u'shtaim*.
Fifty five, twenty two minus fifty five, quick everybody math, פשו ליה
תלתין ותלת *pashu lei tlatin v'tlat*, thirty three. So thirty three... he
only did bad for twenty two years. He did more... he did
good for for... you know, three fifths of his life was doing
good. Okay.
Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי amar rabbi yochanan
mishum rabbi shimon ben yochai *Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai*: מאי דכתיב Mai d'ichtiv, *mai dichtiv*, what's meant, וישמע אליו ויחתר
לו *vayishma elav vayichater lo*. Now actually if the the פסוק pasuk,
*pasuk* is ויעתר לו *vaya'ater lo*. God or was importuned or I
don't know what what English word to use for ויעתר *vaya'ater*. Responded
to him. What? He responded to him. Anyway,
but apparently his his פסוק pasuk *pasuk* had a חת *chet* instead
of an עין ayin *ayin*. And he's going to do a דרשה
drasha. *drasha*. So first we'll read the דרשה drashah *drasha* and then
we'll discuss that. ויעתר לו מיבעי ליה *Vaya'ater lo mibei lei*, it
should have said ויעתר *vaya'ater* with an עין ayin, *ayin*. He was...
he responded to him. So what is ויחתר *vayichater*? It's a חת
*chet* which means like to dig, right? מלמד שעשה לו הקדוש ברוך
הוא כמין מחתרת ברקיע *Melamed she'asa lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu k'min machteret
barakia*. God dug a tunnel for מנשה Menashe *Menashe* to sneak up
to heaven. Okay, because... from מנשה Menashe *Menashe*. Excuse me, to sneak
up to heaven. מחתרת ברקיע *Machteret barakia*. כדי לקבלו בתשובה מפני מידת
הדין *Kedei lekabelo b'teshuva mipnei middat hadin*. Because the the aspect of
God, it's funny like, you know, God like like it's an embodiment
of it, these are all aspects of God. But God's justice wouldn't
allow it. God's, you know, because even now which is a funny
interesting idea. Right, everybody like why does justice allow for תשובה *teshuva*?
But sometimes we say that people are so wicked that God doesn't
let them do תשובה *teshuva*, like it's an explanation like how God
hardens פרעה'ס *Paro's* heart, doesn't give him the opportunity. But מנשה Menashe
*Menashe* actually did do תשובה *teshuva*, right? So if מנשה Menashe *Menashe*
actually did do תשובה *teshuva*, God gave him that opportunity. So we're
supposed to believe that the power of תשובה *teshuva* in general is
in fact that it's not... that you know that it can always
reverse things. But I think what the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* trying to say
is, yeah, but sometimes it really stretch stretches credulity or our sense
of justice. You know, sometimes we understand people, you know, have remorse,
whatever, you know, they're even though it's רחמים *rachamim*, it's a רחמים
*rachamim* we understand. Sometimes the רחמים *rachamim* seems like to allow a
תשובה *teshuva* and allow the תשובה *teshuva* to allow some all the
evil that somebody did to be like wiped away seems to violate
any sense of like right, you know, of justice. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says yeah, but even so God's going to make it
happen. And you know, so that's that imagery that God Himself is
like sneaking and digging a tunnel to avoid His own מידת הדין
*middat hadin* to allow מנשה Menashe, *Menashe* to do it. Very powerful
imagery. Now, how about the fact that it actually says ויעתר *vaya'ater*?
So if you look here at the at the side, right, in
the מסורת הש"ס *Masoret HaShas* in the brackets, it says בפסוק כתיב
ksiv, ויעתר לו *b'pasuk ketiv vaya'ater lo*. וכן העתיק לעיל *v'chein he'etik
l'eil*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* itself a minute ago had quoted the
פסוק pasuk ויעתר *pasuk vaya'ater*. ואפשר דבדברי הימים שהיה לפני רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי היה כתוב ויחתר *v'efshar d'beDivrei HaYamim shehaya lifnei Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai haya katuv vayichater*. He maybe actually had a different version
of the text. לאו אימא דכתב תוספות בשבת *Lav eima dechtav Tosafot
b'Shabbat*. And תוספות *Tosafot* in in certain places points out that sometimes
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and תנאים *Tannaim* or whatever had slightly different
versions of the text than we did. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
something. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* seems sensitive to this. I don't understand what
רש"י'ס *Rashi's* answer is. If you look at the fourth line of
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* from the top, ויחתר לו ומבחוץ כתיב ksiv ויעתר
לו *Vayichater lo u'mibachutz ketiv vaya'ater lo*. On the outside it says
ויעתר לו *vaya'ater lo*. So what does he think? There's like somewhere
underneath the word it says ויחתר *vayichater*? Like he's bothered. The word
is ויעתר לו *vaya'ater lo*, but maybe... so I don't know, is
he saying he's doing some דרשה drashah *drasha* for some hidden meaning
of the word? I don't know what רש"י *Rashi* says. Alright, moving
on. ואמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי *V'amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*: מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv *mai dichtiv*, what's
meant, בראשית ממלכות יהויקים yehoyakim בן יאשיהו *bereshit mamlechut Yehoyakim ben Yoshiyahu*.
In the beginning of the kingdom of יהויקים Yehoyakim *Yehoyakim*. וכתיב בראשית
ממלכות צדקיהו tzidkiyahu *u'chtiv bereshit mamlechut Tzidkiyahu*, in the beginning of צדקיהו
tzidkiyahu *Tzidkiyahu*. So what bothers him is it could have said בראשונה
*barishona* or בשנה ראשונה *bashana rishona*. So בראשית *bereshit* obviously evokes the
first בראשית *bereshit* of the תורה Torah. *Torah*. Okay. ועד האידנא לא
הוו מלכי *V'ad idna lo havu malchei*? So what do you mean?
Oh, it was בראשית *bereshit*, it was like the beginning of all
things. What, you were the first person to become a king? So
the word בראשית *bereshit* is a powerful word. אלא ביקש הקדוש ברוך
הוא להחזיר את העולם כולו לתוהו ובוהו *Ela bikesh HaKadosh Baruch Hu
lehachazir et ha'olam kulo l'tohu vavohu*. So it evokes that original בראשית
*bereshit*. God wanted to start all over again, okay? Turned the whole
world back to void and nothingness and begin again. בשביל יהויקים Yehoyakim
*Bishvil Yehoyakim*. Because of the evil of... of Yehoyakim. So that's בראשית
ממלכות יהויקים. מסתכל בדורו ונתקררה דעתו. Mistakel bedoro venitkara daato. But he
looked at the generation, at the people, and he said, oh, at
least the people are righteous or not totally so evil. So that
allowed him to say, we're not going to start again. ביקש הקדוש
ברוך הוא לעשות עולם כולו תוהו ובוהו בשביל דורו של צדקיהו. Bikesh
hakadosh baruch hu laasot olam kulo tohu vavohu bishvil doro shel Tzidkiyahu.
Now, in the time of Tzidkiyahu, it was the reverse. All the
people were wicked, and God wanted to reverse the world to תוהו
ובוהו. tohu vavohu. נסתכל בצדקיהו, Nistakel beTzidkiyahu, but then he looked at
Tzidkiyahu, ונתקררה דעתו, venitkara daato, and he cooled down and he said,
okay, at least Tzidkiyahu is righteous, so maybe there's some saving hope
for the world. I'm just going to go quickly because of the
time, yeah.
So at the end of Yehoyakim's reign and the beginning of Tzidkiyahu's
reign, the righteous people were all carried into captivity.
Oh, right, right, right. Thank you for mentioning that. Right, Rashi says
that. I forgot to mention that. Which is, right, how did things
reverse themselves so quickly? So this is the whole idea that in
the beginning of the of the מלכות malchut of the of the,
what do you call it, of the Babylonian exile, החרש והמסגר, hachoresh
vehamasger, all the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and all the and all
the righteous people were taken to בבל Bavel first, and they were
taken at the end of Yehoyakim's reign so that by Tzidkiyahu, they
weren't left. Yes, thank you.
That's how it reversed itself so quickly.
Okay, where were we? ובצדקיהו נמי כתיב ויעש הרע בעיני השם. UveTzidkiyahu
nami ktiv vayaas hara be'einei Hashem. What do you mean Tzidkiyahu was
righteous? It says he did the evil. שהיה
בידו למחות ולא מיחה, Shehaya beyado limchot velo micha, because he had
the ability to protest and he did not protest. So it's being,
what do they say, like these people that are quiet and by
through their silence are enablers.
So, actually I was just reading yesterday in the New York Times,
an op-ed by by Nicholas Kristof about the whole issue going on
like with Weinstein and with abuse about women and so on, and
he said, and you know, he had a couple of points, and
one of two of them made me think about the דף. daf.
One of them was that he said, you know, the classic thing
about being the enabler and the silent bystander, and he said, you
know, there has to be there has to be consequences not just
for the perpetrator, but for the people that were also the bystanders
and could have done something, that were the enablers. That's number one.
And the other thing he said was, and this remember the גמרא
Gemara we had the גמרא Gemara before, which is like that it
was
the I remember the אגדתא agadata mentioned, I don't remember where the
גמרא Gemara. was linked to, like the גמרא gemara said that the
taking off of the ring of אחשורוש Achashverosh was more powerful than
all the words of all the prophets, was a similar גמרא Gemara
before, right, about how when bad started to happen, that's when they
did תשובה more than they ever did before. So he quoted what's
her name, from the CFO of Facebook, Sheryl
Sandberg, Sandberg, right. Anyway, so she said that like, you know, all
the sensitivity training in the world is whatever, but she said
one dismissal of some high-position person because of the way he acts
is better than all the sensitivity training in the world. You know,
so it makes me think exactly of that גמרא. Gemara So consequences
is what matters.
Anyway, so that's by Tzidkiyahu, you change her her position to, like,
ויעש הרע, is like, oh, because he left it there.
Oh, maybe, I don't know, that's a good question. Maybe this is
the point we wanted to make here though. Okay, ואמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai. מאי דכתיב, Mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the verse, איש חכם
נשפט את איש אויל, ish chacham nishpat et ish evil, the wise
person judged the foolish person, ורגז ושחק ואין נחת, veragaz vesachak ve'ein
nachat, and he was angry and laughed and there was no satisfaction.
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar hakadosh baruch hu, so God is the
איש חכם. ish chacham. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא כעסתי על אחז, Amar
hakadosh baruch hu kaasati al Achaz, I got angry at Achaz, ונתתיו
ביד מלכי דמשק, unetatv biyad malchei Damesek, so he so the איש
אויל ish evil is a bad king, God judged the bad kings,
ורגז ושחק veragaz vesachak is sometimes God gets angry and responds by
making them suffer, sometimes God says let's see what it is if
they're successful, and whether the bad kings were had it bad or
whether they were successful, either way, there was no satisfaction. They kept
on doing their evil. Okay? So when it came to when it
came to, where were we? אחז, Achaz, and I gave him the
מלכי דמשק, malchei Damesek, he was handed over to the kings of
Damascus, he was taken captive. זיבח וקיטר לאלוהיהם, Zivach vekiter leloheihem, it
didn't do any good, the fact that he suffered, he went and
they offered to their gods. שנאמר כי אלוהי מלכי ארם המה מעזרים
אותם להם אזבח, Shene'emar ki elohei malchei Aram hema me'azrim otam lahem
ezbach, so because this is what Achaz said, the gods of the
kings of Aram, they're the ones that are helping them, that's why
they're successful over me. להם אזבח, Lahem ezbach,
I will, so therefore let's I'm going to switch sides, I'm going
to sacrifice to them, ויעזרוני והם היו לו להכשילו ולכל ישראל, vaya'azruni
vehem hayu lo lehachshilo ulechol Yisrael, okay, and they will help me,
and they were his downfall. So when bad things happened, they abandoned
me. So fine.
So where were we? I lost my place. Oh,
שחקתי עם אמציהו, Sachakti im Amatziahu, so by Amatziahu I tried the
opposite, I made things good for him. ונתתי מלכי אדום בידו, Venatati
malchei Edom biyado, and I handed over the kings of Edom into
his hands. הביא אלוהיהם והשתחווה להם, Hevi eloheihem vehishtachava lahem, what did
he do? He took the gods of the conquered people, and he
decided he was gonna worship them. So right, here, you know, makes
no sense. He should have recognized that it was God who did
it for him. שנאמר ויהי אחר בוא אמציהו מהכות את אדומים, Shene'emar
vayehi achar bo Amatziahu mehachot et Edomim, when he returned from smiting
the Edomites, ויבא את אלוהי בני שעיר, vayave et elohei bnei Se'ir,
he brought the gods of the people of Se'ir, ויעמידם לו לאלוהים,
vaya'amidam lo lelohim, and he erected them for himself. for god and
ולפניהם ישתחווה velifnehem yishtachaveh in front of them he would bow down,
ולהם יקטר velahem yekater to them he would offer incense. אמר רב
פפא היינו דאמרי אינשי amar rav pappa hainu d'amrei inshi that's what
people say, בכי ליה למר דלא ידע bachi lei lemar d'lo yada
חייכי ליה למר דלא ידע chaichi lei lemar d'lo yada cry for
the person who doesn't know, laugh for the person who doesn't know,
ווי ליה למר דלא ידע בין טב לביש vai lei lemar d'lo
yada bein tav levish woe to the person who doesn't know between
good and evil. So whether bad things or good things happen, it
makes no difference to you, you are just committed to your own
convictions and you don't take heed regardless of what's happening. Okay,
ויבאו כל שרי מלך בבל וישבו בשער התוך vayavo'u kol sarei melech
bavel vayeshvu beshaar hatoch so this is by the destruction of the
בית המקדש beis hamikdash right all of and I'm not exactly sure
I guess because they mentioned צדקיהו tzidkiyahu and and you know whoever
it was and יהויקים so we're also so now we're talking in
the area of the downfall of מלכות יהודה. malchus yehuda. So all
of the all of the officers of the king of בבל bavel
came and they sat and they sat in the gate of תוך.
toch. So what's תוך? toch? תווך, tavech, thank you. Oh, so he's
right, תווך. tavech. תווך tavech is middle, you're correct. I misread it,
תווך. tavech. So אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan, משום רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי מקום שמחתכין בו הלכות. makom shemechatchen bo halachos. It's the
place where they would would be so I think I was sort
of reading it because of the way the גמרא Gemara reads it.
So if you look at רש״י rashi התוך hatoch לשון חותך lashon
choteich like a ה hei and a ח ches sort of exchanged.
It's the place where והיינו בהר הבית ובאזרה שהיו יושבים סנהדרין. vehainu
behar habayis uv'azarah shehayu yoshvim sanhedrin. So there they were and they
took the gates where the סנהדרין sanhedrin would sit. Gates always evoke
that idea of a בית דין beis din and a court and
so on, right, where they would be cutting the justice and they
and they made it into like a, you know, a place for
just, you know, for for doing
what do you call
for like inappropriate behavior. Okay,
so where
were we? מקום שמחתכין בו הלכות. makom shemechatchen bo halachos. אמר רב
פפא amar rav pappa היינו דאמרי אינשי hainu d'amrei inshi and that's
what people say
באתרא דמרי תלי ליה זייניה b'asra d'marei tali lei zainiei in the
same place that the master would would hang up his weapons תמן
קולבא רעיא קוזיא תלי taman kulba ra'aya kuzya tali there like a
lowly shepherd is now hanging up his like a pitcher, you know,
so like you know like the outrage, you know this was right
the the mighty fallen but also like the sense of like you
know the degrading of like this was like such a special and
holy place and now look here how it's sort of being you
know the complete reversal. Okay yeah רש״י rashi says
נהפך למושב לצים nehepach lemoshav leitzim right it just became some place
of like entertainment and of foolishness and of so on. Yeah Charlie?
Might this have been referral to the fact that it was רשעים
resha'im who were deciding the הלכה? halacha?
No, I mean maybe maybe I don't think so.
צדקיהו was maybe I don't think so.
אמר רב חסדא אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא amar rav chisda amar
rabbi yirmiah bar abba מאי דכתיב mai dechsiv? what's meant by the
verse? על שדה al sadeh now we're sort of going to be
looking you know sort of at a bigger picture about the evil
kings and so on okay. What's meant by the verse על שדה
איש עצל עברתי al sadeh ish atzel avarti I passed by the
field of a lazy person ועל כרם אדם חסר לב v'al kerem
adam chasar lev by the vineyard of a person who is lacking
of understanding והנה עלה כולו קמשונים ve'hineh ala kulo kimshonim
it's all been filled with thorns and thistles כסו פניו חרולים kasu
fanav charullim and covered with weeds וגדר אבניו נהרסה v'geder avanav nehersa
and the walls of the stone walls have been broken through. Okay
so who are all these people? And the end of it, breaking
through the wall is probably what the hinge, the hook was cause
that's evoking the destruction of the temple. So now we're going to
work backwards. Okay על שדה איש עצל עברתי al sadeh ish atzel
avarti a lazy person, זה אחז zeh achaz that's אחז. achaz. Each
one of them were like lazy in terms of like restoring the
people to righteousness okay and then things got worse and worse okay.
זה אחז zeh achaz ועל כרם אדם חסר לב זה מנשה v'al
kerem adam chasar lev zeh menashe so we're now in מנשה. Menashe.
והנה עלה כולו קמשונים זה אמון ve'hineh ala kulo kimshonim zeh amon
and אמון amon because we're going to see later that it basically
says that אמון amon like you know the the מזבח mizbe'ach was
filled with like it's going to say like cobwebs because it was
because nobody was you know because nobody was offering in the בית
המקדש. beis hamikdash. Okay so like everybody's not paying attention, things are
getting worse, it's like filling with
weeds. כסו פניו חרולים זה יהויקים. kasu fanav charullim zeh yehoyakim. וגדר
אבניו נהרסה זה צדקיהו. v'geder avanav nehersa zeh tzidkiyahu. So even though
צדקיהו didn't do anything wrong but by his or did something wrong
he was a passive enabler, but anyway by his time you know
already now now the walls are being broken through. שנחרב בית המקדש
בימיו. shenechrav beis hamikdash beyamav. ואמר רב חסדא v'amar rav chisda and
now and we're going to fill in some of these blanks later.
ואמר רב חסדא אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא v'amar rav chisda amar
rabbi yirmiah bar abba ארבע כיתות אין מקבלות פני שכינה arba kitos
ein mekablot pnei shechinah four groups of people don't get a chance
to receive the divine presence. כת לצים kat leitzim the mockers, כת
שקרנים kat shakranim the liars, כת חניפים kat chanifim the flatterers, וכת
מספרי לשון הרע vekat mesaprei lashon hara those that speak evil that
speak evil tongue. So all of these by the way have to
do with like speech you know and about lack of honesty or
integrity or like forthrightness in speech.
And it's interesting right because it's אין מקבלות פני שכינה ein mekablot
pnei shechinah does that mean לעולם הבא? l'olam haba? Are we talking
about like prayer right you know I mean thinking that speech and
good speech and encountering God and prayer and so on, so it's
interesting like why these are specifically you know identified.
כת לצים דכתיב kat leitzim dechtiv משך mashach one who speaks falsehood
will not will not be proper in front of me, right? And
that ties into the discussion we quoted that verse earlier by the
נחש Nachash story. כת חניפים Kat Chanifim the flatterers דכתיב d'chtiv כי
לא לפניו חנף יבוא, ki lo lefanav chaneph yavo, God will not
tolerate in front of him flattery, it will not come in front
of him. כת מספרי לשון הרע Kat mesaprei lashon hara דכתיב כי
לא אל חפץ רשע אתה, ki lo el chafetz resha atah, you
are not a God who desires evil, so it doesn't actually say
לשון הרע. lashon hara. Right. רע Ra it says, it says if
you look at the earlier פסוק, pasuk, it seems that the context
לא יגורך רע, lo yegurcha ra, evil does not dwell with you.
צדיק אתה ולא יהיה במגורך רע, Tzadik atah v'lo yihiyeh b'migurecha ra,
you are righteous and it will not be within where dwells within
you evil. ואמר רב חסדא אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, V'amar Rav
Chisda amar Rabi Yirmiyah bar Abba, so a lot of these מימרות
meimrot of the same אמורא. Amora. מאי דכתיב, mai dechsiv, so they're
not all directly relevant, what's meant by the verse לא תאונה אליך
רעה, lo te'uneh elecha ra'ah, evil will not will not befall you,
ונגע לא יקרב באהלך, v'nega lo yikrav b'oholecha, no plague or affliction
will occur in your tent. לא תאונה אליך רעה Lo te'uneh elecha
ra'ah שלא ישלוט בך יצר הרע, shelo yishlot becha yetzer hara,
the evil desire, like presumably here in this context means sexual desire
will not have dominion over you, doesn't mean don't have it, that's
human, but it won't have dominion over you. ונגע לא יקרב באהלך
v'nega lo yikrav b'oholecha
and bad won't occur in your tent, אהלך oholecha often is read
to mean your wife, or context of marital relations with the wife,
שלא תמצא אשתך ספק נדה בשעה שתבוא מן הדרך. shelo timtza ishtecha
safek niddah b'sha'ah shetavo min haderech. You've just come back from a
long journey, you want to finally have sex with your wife, speaking
to the man, right? And it's always speaking to the man. And
then she's a ספק נדה. safek niddah. And as Rashi says, ספק
נדה safek niddah is worse than being a ודאי נדה, vadai niddah,
because a ודאי נדה vadai niddah you're able to say, okay, whatever,
I have to hold myself back, but ספק נדה safek niddah you're
grappling with your own rationalizing and trying to well, probably not, and
this and that. Okay, so that won't happen to you. Okay.
דבר אחר, Davar acher, another explanation, לא תאונה אליך רעה lo te'uneh
elecha ra'ah שלא יבעתוך חלומות רעים והרהורים רעים. shelo yeva'atucha chalomot ra'im
v'hirhurim ra'im. You won't be disturbed by bad dreams and bad thoughts.
So הרהורים רעים hirhurim ra'im sometimes means, especially given the previous context,
like sexual thoughts which might lead to you know to having a
seminal emission at night, but יבעתוך, yeva'atucha, like disturb you, just means
you won't be disturbed by bad dreams, like bad dreams can sometimes
be very disturbing to people. ונגע לא יקרב באהלך v'nega lo yikrav
b'oholecha שלא יהיה לך בן או תלמיד שמקדיח תבשילו ברבים. shelo yihiyeh
lecha ben o talmid shemakdiach tavshilo barabbim. So now we're off of
the sort of of the sexual topic. You won't have bad here
your tent is not necessarily your tent of your wife, but your
tent of either your family in sense of your children or the
tent of תורה. Torah. So therefore you will not have children or
or students who go and like burn your you know burn your
your stew in public, meaning that you know, so A, so they
won't go off the דרך, derech, and if they do go off
the דרך, derech, they won't do it in public that it winds
up looking back looking bad about you.
Won't burn their stew in public, but the point is still the
same anyway. Whatever even if they go off the דרך, derech, they
won't do it in a way that then reflects upon you. Okay.
עד כאן ברכו אביו. Ad kan bercho aviv. Zion says כגון ישו
הנוצרי. kegon Yeshu HaNotzri.
Oh really? Oh.
Interesting thing that's been edited out, כגון ישו הנוצרי. kegon Yeshu HaNotzri.
Yeah. So why I don't know of all things why that would
be the one that would be identified, but okay.
ישו, Yeshu, you know, it was viewed as him, right?
I understand, but is that connected to is that connected to ואמר
רב חסדא אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא? V'amar Rav Chisda amar Rabi
Yirmiyah bar Abba? I understand that we have the story about ישו
הנוצרי, Yeshu HaNotzri, but of all things to specifically make it about
him, I don't know, it's interesting. But thank you, yeah, I have
to keep on checking the different גרסאות girsaot here. There's a whole
passage coming up that's like a 10 lines about also that was
edited out that we'll have to, no not today, later. Michael, could
you respond to that email about covering me for the דף? daf?
Okay.
Alright. So, okay. Where were we? עד כאן ברכו אביו. Ad kan
bercho aviv. Until this point, his father blessed him. Now, whose father?
You could just say it's talking about like in general if somebody's
father would give this type of a blessing and now we're going
to say a mother's going to give a blessing. But Rashi specifically
says דוד David is giving this ברכה berachah to שלמה. Shlomo. And
now we're going to talk about the ברכות berachot that שלמה's Shlomo
mother gives to him, because I guess דוד David is the writer
of ספר תהילים, Sefer Tehillim, but I don't know why we're specifically
making it about that. Anyway, this is the blessing of the father.
As Rashi says, these are the types of concerns that a father
has, you know, about the about the sexual issues and about the
and about well, I don't know about the bad dreams, but anyway,
about students that you're going to have, I think that's sort of
the very type of male concerns as through as what the גמרא
Gemara is saying. ומכאן ואילך ברכתו אמו. U'mikan v'ilech birchato imo. And
now starts the blessings that the mother gives. Okay. And it goes
and as Rashi points out, like it just sounds like there's a
different it sounds like there's a different the content is a little
different and the tone and it sounds like we're starting a new
point. כי מלאכיו יצוה לך, Ki malachav yetzaveh lach, your the his
angels God will command to you, לשמרך בכל דרכיך, lishmorcha bechol derachecha,
to watch you in all your paths, על כפים ישאונך, al kapayim
yisau'necha, will lift you up on his hands on his palms, על
שחל ופתן תדרוך, al shachal vafeten tidroch, you will trample on like
these snakes, I think that's
true how. So that's the type of things that a mother is
concerned about, right? That you should be safe and you should be
protected and no harm should come to you. Okay, so those are
the blessings of the mother. עד כאן ברכת אמו. ad kan birchas
imo. מכאן ואילך ברכת השמים, mikan va'ilach birchas hashamayim, and from this
point on God is blessing. כי בי חשק ואפלטהו, ki bi chashak
va'afalteihu, because he had desire or trust in me and I will
save him. אשגבהו, asagveihu, because now this is in God's voice obviously,
I will save him. אשגבהו, asagveihu, I will save him, כי ידע
שמי, ki yada shemi, he knows my name. יקראני ואענהו, yikra'eini ve'eneihu,
he calls to me, I'd answer. עמו אנכי בצרה, imo anochi betzarah,
I am with him in times of trouble. אחלצהו ואכבדהו, achaltzeihu va'achabdeihu,
I will save him and I will give him honor. אורך ימים
אשביעהו ואראהו בישועתי, orech yamim asbi'eihu ve'ar'eihu bishu'asi, I will give him
long life and show him in my salvation. אמר ריש לקיש, amar
Reish Lakish, מאי דכתיב? Okay, back to... I don't know what back
to...
the psalm that משה, Moshe, actually I think משה Moshe wrote 90
to whatever.
Oh, it says תפילה למשה tefillah leMoshe at the beginning, so then
it's interesting, not in 91 but in 90.
I read a note somewhere that he wrote it.
The גמרא Gemara says that he wrote 90 through 99.
So I wonder why רש"י sort of says it means דוד David
and שלמה, Shlomo, interesting. Okay.
אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, מאי דכתיב, what's meant by the
verse? וימנע מרשעים אורם וזרוע רמה תשבר. veyimana mersha'im oram vezroa ramah
tishaver. God withheld from the wicked their light and the
outstretched arm God will break. מפני מה ע"ין של רשעים תלויה? mipnei
mah ayin shel rasha'im teluyah? Maybe this is because we also discussed
before the חטף ויעטר, chataf vaya'ater, although that wasn't our text. But
why is the ע"ין ayin, of
רשעים rasha'im תלויה, teluyah, suspended? Like in the text it's written above
the word, it's not in the word.
And without the ע"ין, it would read רשים, rashim, the poor. So,
גמרא Gemara says, ועי"ן ve'ayin תלויה, teluyah,
כיון שנעשה אדם רש מלמטה, keivan shena'asah adam rash milmata, to tell
you that when a person is poor below, and here the way
רש"י reads it, it does not mean in the way the גמרא
Gemara, seems to be going to read it. It does not mean
poor in material goods. It means poor in terms of, like, friends,
like if people are all attacking somebody and like no, he has
no friends. So then, if that's true, נעשה רש מלמעלה, na'asah rash
milma'alah, you know or it leads him to or you know, as
the way רש"י reads it, that he... God does not have favor
in His eyes either. Like you know, it's sort of like, מצא
חן ושכל טוב בעיני אלוהים ואדם. matza chein veseichel tov be'einei Elokim
ve'adam. Like
you know, if somebody is, people like him down here, whatever, it's
an indication also about above, and the same in the reverse. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ולא נכתביה כלל. velo nischivei klal. So if
that's what the message of the פסוק is, why does it write
with an ע"ין, רשעים? rasha'im? Just write רשים. rashim. ר' יוחנן ור'
אלעזר, R' Yochanan veR' Elazar, חד אמר מפני כבודו של דוד, chad
amar mipnei kevodo shel David, because it's not always true. Because it's
only true about when רשעים rasha'im don't have friends, then you know
that God doesn't like them, of course, if they're wicked God won't
like them anyway. But sometimes righteous people don't have friends because people
don't like the good stuff they're doing. And then that point wouldn't
be true. So that's why it's written רשעים rasha'im and רשים. rashim.
Because there are righteous people who didn't have friends and it's not
true about. For the honor of King דוד, David, right? King דוד
David had a very hard... people always running after him, he had
all these rebellions, שאול, Shaul, the whole thing, and it's not true
about King דוד. David. וחד אמר מפני כבודו של נחמיה בן חכליה,
vechad amar mipnei kevodo shel Nechemya ben Chachalyah, because נחמיה Nechemya had
all this opposition, okay? And nevertheless he was righteous. So it's funny,
it's like, okay, this is the message, but it's not really true,
or it's not true all the time. So anyway, okay. All the
prophets,
ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, etc. I'm just going to keep on going.
ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu,
according to most opinions, lived long before דוד David and נחמיה. Nechemya.
Yeah, that's true, the whole question of when he lived. Okay, תנא
מנא לן, tana mna lan, מנשה היה שונה חמשים וחמשה פנים בתורת
כהנים. Menashe hayah shoneh chamishim vechamishah panim beToras Kohanim. So we're back,
remember
like we're making all these kings even when they're wicked we're saying
there were great aspects to them. מנשה Menashe did תשובה according to
one version 33 years. And now they're, but they're also all תלמידי
חכמים. talmidei chachamim. I remember the whole story with, what's his name,
with
ירבעם, Yerovam, right? He went out to the field and they darshened
all this amazing תורה. Torah Okay, so מנשה Menashe, would teach 55
different, different like דרשות drashos in ויקרא. Vayikra. Like you know, halachic,
you know, different ways of halachically interpreting the פסוקים, pesukim, on every
פסוק 55 ways. כנגד שני מלכותו, keneged shenei malchuso, according to the
years of his kingdom. אחאב שמונים
וחמשה. Achav shemonim vechamishah. And now we're explicitly saying, right, all this
תורה Torah scholarship was had by all these, all these wicked kings.
אחאב 85 different interpretations of the verse. ירבעם מאה ושלשה, Yerovam me'ah
ushloshah, and ירבעם Yerovam 103.
And I want, maybe another part of the message is not just
that people are complex and they're not all bad or all good
or whatever, but also, don't assume that just because somebody's a תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham, you know, means that they're a good person. And
also, and this is a hard religious message, like you know, well,
if there are bad people who are religious, obviously the religion is
not, people will say, like, so what good is the religion, right?
What good is religion if people can still do this type of
disgusting thing and then think that they're religious, right? And go ahead
and שבת Shabbos and כשרות Kashrus and the whole thing. You know,
the גמרא's Gemara sort of like acknowledges it, like you could have,
right, although I wouldn't say that these kings were religious, they were
עובדי עבודה זרה. ovdei avodah zarah. I don't know how good they
were with שבת Shabbos or כשרות Kashrus even, although some גמרות Gemaros
actually have some of them being... עובדי עבודה זרה ovdei avodah zarah
and being very careful about כשרות, Kashrus, but that's a different story.
But anyway, but the point is is like, it's, you know, A,
we'd like to believe we do it because God said so, but
B, we'd like to believe that it does, you know, it does
do a lot of good, but it's not always going to do
good, right? There are people that are going to be wicked and
whatever and it doesn't matter if they do all this stuff. And
you could have somebody that's a huge תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and
still be the wickedest king of Israel. Yeah.
Is the room here to say they read so much stuff in
there including heretical things?
That's interesting. I'm not sure the, I don't think that's the tone
of the גמרא, and I also don't know if the context sort
of speaks about like, this, their issue being one of heresy. You
know, heresy is like עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, and the גמרא even
imagines you could be an עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah and
sort of still believing in God because you just believe in multiple
gods as it were. You know, you're worshipping Moav's god, not Israel's
god. So I don't know. Maybe, but I'm not getting that as
the tone—I'm not saying it's wrong, you know, but I'm not getting
that as the tone. Okay. אבשלום אין לו
חלק לעולם הבא. Avshalom ein lo chelek l'olam haba. Look, תניא, tanya,
תנו
רבנן,
Tanu
Rabbanan, אבשלום אין לו חלק לעולם הבא. Avshalom ein lo chelek l'olam
haba. אבשלום Avshalom doesn't have a portion. Now, if you want, I
even forget, who are the four הדיוטות hedyotot that don't have a
חלק chelek in עולם הבא? olam haba? The four הדיוטות hedyotot are
בלעם דואג אחיתופל וגחזי. Bilaam, Doeg, Achitophel v'Geichazi. Okay, and so here
we are in אבשלום, Avshalom, and אבשלום Avshalom is like, he's a
הדיוט hedyot but he's also sort of in the king's family. Okay,
so he says אבשלום Avshalom doesn't have a portion in the world
to come.
Where were we? שנאמר ויכו את אבשלום וימיתהו. shene'emar vayaku es Avshalom
vayamisuhu. They smote him and they killed him. ויכו בעולם הזה וימיתהו
לעולם הבא. Vayaku b'olam hazeh vayamisuhu l'olam haba. All right. Not as
good as the other דרשה. תניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום
רבי מאיר: Tanya, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar Omer mishum Rabbi Meir: אחז
ואחזיה וכל מלכי ישראל. Achaz v'Achazyah v'chol malchei Yisrael. So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir clearly wanted to not make it such an exclusive club.
Okay. There's a lot of other people I would put on that
list who doesn't have a portion in the world to come. Okay.
So אחז ואחזיה Achaz v'Achazyah and all of the kings of Israel
שכתוב בהם, shekasuv bahem, so אחז ואחזיה Achaz v'Achazyah were מלכי יהודה,
malchei Yehudah, right? בימי, b'imei, the beginning of... what is it? בימי
אבי חזקיהו מן העם... b'imei Avi Chizkiyahu min Ha-Am... no no no,
that's ישעיהו. Yeshayahu.
What is it? חזון ישעיהו בן אמוץ אשר חזה על יהודה וירושלים
בימי עוזיהו יותם אחז חזקיהו מלכי יהודה. Chazon Yeshayahu ben Amoz asher
chazah al Yehudah v'Yirushalayim b'imei Uzziyahu Yosam Achaz Chizkiyahu malchei Yehudah.
Okay.
So anyway, so אחז Achaz and, where were we? אחז ואחזיה Achaz
v'Achazyah were מלכי יהודה malchei Yehudah and רש״י Rashi says he has
this by a מסורה. Masorah. And then וכל מלכי ישראל שכתוב בהם
ויעש הרע בעיני השם, v'chol malchei Yisrael shekasuv bahem vayas hara b'einei
Hashem, and all of the Israelite kingdom, all of the kings of
the Israelite kingdom that it says they did the evil in the
eyes of God, even though it also says that by the kings
of the יהודה Yehudah kingdom. Nevertheless, this is his approach. These two
kings of יהודה Yehudah and all of the kings of the Israelite
kingdom that it says they did the evil in the eyes of
God, לא חיים ולא נידונים, lo chaim v'lo nidonim, are not resurrected
in the time of תחיית המתים techiyas hamaysim and are not going
to be judged. Is that the same as אין לו חלק לעולם
הבא? ein lo chelek l'olam haba? We're going to see that phrase
coming up later in the משנה, Mishnah, exactly how that matches. Is
it the same or how it's different? It's not clear. But the
idea is that at the time of resurrection, after everybody gets resurrected,
the רשעים reshaim will also be resurrected and there will be a
time of judgment and then the, you know, the צדיקים tzaddikim will
live and the רשעים reshaim will go back to גיהנום. Gehennom. Okay,
or will go to גיהנום. Gehennom. So and so some people are
going to be resurrected and judged, and that presumably is better than
not even being resurrected at all. Okay, so these people are not
going to be resurrected and judged. וגם דם נקי. V'gam dam naki.
Now back to מנשה. Menashe, וגם דם נקי שפך מנשה הרבה מאד,
V'gam dam naki shafach Menashe harbei me'od, he spilled innocent blood, עד
אשר מלא ירושלים פה לפה, ad asher milei Yerushalayim peh l'peh, until
he filled Jerusalem from one opening to the next with blood. לבד
מחטאתו אשר החטיא יהודה לעשות הרע בעיני השם. Levad michataso asher hechti
Yehudah la'asos hara b'einei Hashem. So besides he was a murderer and
he spilled all this innocent blood, besides all the other evil that
he did, right, to cause the people to sin. This was his
own sin and then he did all the evil to cause the
people to sin. You sometimes wonder like, you know, if Shakespeare had
done something based on this, like it's sort of like, you know,
like... he was really good at it with Macbeth and other things,
you know. Anyway, הכא
תרגימו, hacha targinu, what was this blood that he spilled that filled
Jerusalem from one end to the other with blood? הכא תרגימו, hacha
targinu, here they interpret it, שהרג ישעיהו, sheharag Yeshayahu, that he killed
ישעיהו הנביא. Yeshayahu HaNavi. That's pretty darn bad. I mean ישעיהו הנביא.
Yeshayahu HaNavi. So that's one person, but it's as if he was
such a great person as if he filled Jerusalem from one opening
with blood to the next. במערבא אמרי, B'ma'arava amri, in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael they say, שעשה צלם משוי אלף בני אדם, she'asah tzelem
masui elef b'nei adam,
that this is connected to his עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. He made
an idol that had to be carried by a thousand people. ובכל
יום ויום הורג כולהם. U'bechol yom va-yom horeg kulohem.
And he would like carry it and move it I guess, and
every day the, the way רש״י Rashi explains it, not that he
would kill a thousand all of the people, but that the moving
of the idol would like would kill the people that were moving
it because it was so weighty. Okay. So it was all connected
to his
idolatry. כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבה בר בר חנה ששקולה נשמה של
צדיק אחד כנגד כולם כולם, K'man azla ha d'Amar Rabbah bar bar
Chana she'shkula nishama shel tzaddik echad k'neged kulam kulam, who does it
go like
the
statement that the soul of one Okay, כתיב, verse says פסל pessel
and כתיב פסילים. psilim.
So that he made an idol and then it says he made
idols. So which one is it? אמר amar. רבי יוחנן, בתחילה עשה
לו פרצוף אחד. b'techila asa lo partzuf echad. At the beginning he
made this one idol, right, which he sort of put in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and he had it, gave it one face.
ובסוף עשה לו ארבעה פרצופים. u'vasof asa lo arba'ah partzufim. Then he
gave it four faces in all directions, כדי שתקניט שכינה. kedei she'taknit
Shechina. He wanted to do it again like להכעיס lehach'is God. Right,
he wanted God in any direction, I mean God sees all directions,
but whatever. Okay, no matter where you look you see the face
of the idol just to spite God. אחז העמידו בעליה. Achaz he'emido
ba'aliyah. Now אחז Achaz put this idol in the, in the attic
of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ואת המזבחות אשר על
הגג עלית אחז v'es hamizbechos asher al hagag aliyas Achaz or maybe
not even the attic of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, his עליה.
aliyah. Okay, the, he put his עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you know,
not in public as much. Okay, although they were higher up. But
anyway, on the, they you know, that they were on the, on
the rooftops. מנשה העמידו בהיכל. Menashe he'emido b'heichal. מנשה put the צלם
tzelem in the היכל, Heichal, right? That's one of the whole, you
know, מנשה putting it in the היכל, Heichal, one of the things
about the תשעה באב Tisha B'Av period. Anyway, מנשה put the idol
in the, in the actual בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash itself. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
וישם את פסל האשרה אשר עשה בבית אשר אמר השם אל דוד
ואל שלמה בנו. vayasem es pessel ha'asheirah asher asa babayis asher amar
Hashem el David v'el Shlomo bno. He, he put it in the
same house that God had said, בבית זה ובירושלים אשר בחרתי מכל
שבטי ישראל אשים את שמי לעולם. babayis zeh uviYerushalayim asher bacharti mikol
shivtei Yisrael asim es shmi l'olam. I will put my name in
this house and this is the one that מנשה puts his idol.
A little bit similar, although this is obviously more of an outrage
to the kings of בבל Bavel who are sitting in the gates
of ירושלים Yerushalayim and in the case of the בית דין Beis
Din and are just having a sport and their fun. Okay, אמון.
Amon. Now, that wasn't enough for אמון. Amon. אמון Amon הכניסו לבית
קדשי הקדשים. hechniso l'veis kadshei hakodashim. He brought it into the Holy
of Holies. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי קצר המצע מהשתרע. ki katzar hamatza mehishtarei'a.
The bed, the couch is too short to stretch out on. והמסכה,
v'hamaseichah, and the literal meaning of the verse is the blanket, צרה
כהתכנס tzarah k'hiskanes is too narrow to cover yourself with. But here
it's going to be the דרשא. drasha. מאי כי קצר המצע מהשתרע?
Mai ki katzar hamatza mehishtarei'a? אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן, Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, כי קצר המצע
זה מלהשתרר עליו שני רעים כאחד. ki katzar hamatza zeh m'lehishtareir alav
shnei rei'im k'echad. So להשתרר lehishtareir is the idea of רעים, rei'im,
friends. So this bed or bedroom or whatever, the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and the קודש הקדשים Kodesh Hakodashim is too narrow to have
two people sleeping in it, like to have two gods in it,
right? Okay.
מאי והמסכה צרה? Mai v'hamaseichah tzarah? And this really seems to be
the hook because מסכה maseichah is, is like the same word used
for פסל, pessel, not just like, you know, not like it's from
the word, I think, probably like the word is... anyway, from the
word of, like, you know, some cast image. אמר רבי שמואל בר
נחמני רבי יונתן כי הוי מטי להאי קרא הוה בכי. Amar Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachmani Rabbi Yonatan ki havai mati l'hai kra havah bachi.
When it would get to this verse he would cry. מי שכתוב
בו, Mi shekasuv bo, כונס כנד מי הים. kones k'ned mei hayam.
The one of whom it said, God, that he gathers like in
a, in a flask all of the waters of the ocean, תעשה
לו מסכה צרה? ta'aseh lo maseichah tzarah? An idol should be his,
his competing wife? Okay, right? The word צרה tzarah like a, like
a co-wife. So the verse is, right, והמסכה, v'hamaseichah, the idol, צרה,
tzarah, became a competing wife כהתכנס k'hiskanes for the one who was
so great that all he can gather up all of the waters
of the sea. Okay, you could also read it כהתכנס k'hiskanes when
it was entered into, brought into the קודש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. Very
powerful imagery. אחז ביטל את העבודה. Achaz bital es ha'avodah. Now let's
go back and talk about, you know, some more about these evil
kings, not necessarily the ones that were on the list of the
משנה. Mishnah. אחז Achaz caused an end to the service in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. וחתם את התורה. v'chasam es haTorah. He sealed
the Torah. It doesn't exactly say what sealing the Torah means, presumably
it means that he like made, stopped people from learning Torah. שנאמר,
Shene'emar, the verse
says, צור תעודה חתום תורה tzur te'udah chasum Torah בלמודי belimudai in
my learners. So he prevented the learning of Torah. מנשה קדר את
האזכרות. Menashe kadar es ha'azkaros. So we mentioned this before by whoever
it was with a different פסוק, not by מנשה, but here we're
associating it with מנשה. מנשה cut out God's names from the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah and according to whatever the earlier story, replaced them
with names of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. והרס את המזבח. v'haras es
hamizbeiach. It wasn't enough that people weren't offering on the altar, he
destroyed the altar. אמון
שרף את התורה. Amon saraf es haTorah. It wasn't enough that people
weren't learning Torah, he burned the Torah. והעלה שממית על גבי המזבח.
v'he'ela shamamis al gabei hamizbeiach. And there were cobwebs on the altar.
I don't know if there were cobwebs on the altar once the
altar is destroyed, but okay, whatever. Maybe the altar was only, was
only sort of injured and not totally destroyed. Anyway, this goes back
to the earlier דרשות drashos about the, pass, you know, walking by
the person's field and he's lazy and all of the stuff is
growing on it and all of the weeds and thistles. So this
is like the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is growing, getting cobwebs from
disuse. One minute. אחז התיר את הערוה. Achaz hitir es ha'erva. אחז
Achaz permitted forbidden sexual relations. מנשה, it wasn't enough to permit it
for the people, בעל אחותו. ba'al achoso. He just despite whatever had
sex with his sister. ואמון בא על אמו. v'Amon ba al imo.
And אמון Amon had sex with his mother. שנאמר Shene'emar כי הוא
אמון הרבה אשמה. ki hu Amon hirbah ashmah. He, he increased the
sin, so like the greatest sin that they can think of, or
not only is it a great sin, but it also, like, it
seemed to be like as the גמרא is going to say, in
spite, that there wasn't really a יצר הרע yetzer hara for this.
רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, Rabbi Yochanan veRabbi Eliezer, חדא אמר ששרף את
התורה. chada amar shesharaf et hatorah. So, so we've had a debate:
what would be the worst sin we could sort of think of
about him? So one is that he burnt a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah וחדא אמר שבא על אמו. vechada amar sheba al imo. אמר
ליה אמו, Amar lei imo, now it's going to explain why it
thinks it's such a big sin. His mother said, כלום יש לך
הנאה ממקום שיצאת ממנו? Klum yesh lecha hana'ah mimakom sheyatzata mimenu? Do
you have any benefit from the place from which you emerged? Right
having sex, you know, and whatever, intercourse in that same place that
you emerged from, like, where is that which is interesting, right, the
sense that Eros or
know eroticism comes from like a sense of like unfamiliarity or difference
or whatever, it's interesting. Anyway, אמר לה, amar lah, כלום אני עושה
אלא להכעיס את בוראי. Klum ani oseh ela lehachis et bori. So
I'm not doing it because I want to, I'm just doing it
to spite God. כי אתא יהויקים, ki ata Yehoyakim, אמר. Now when
יהויקים came, right, he said, קמאי לא ידעו לארגוזי כלום. Kama'ei lo
yadu le'argezei klum. Ha! They didn't even begin to know how to
anger
God. אנו כלום אנו צריכים לאורו? Anu klum anu tzrichim le'oro? Why
do we even need God? What, because God gives us the sun
and God gives us life? האי אית לנו זהב פרווים דאנן משתמשין
ביה. Hai it lanu zehav parvayim de'anan mishtamshin bei. We have this
beautiful pure gold that that gives us light. It's pretty funny. Like
why they take gold? Not fire, I mean anyway. Okay, anyway, יטול
אורו, yitlo oro, לקצץ את
אורו! lekatzetz et oro! Let God take His light away, who needs
God? אמרו לו, amaru lo, it's just pretty funny because him, here
this issue of what do you call it? Of of like angering
God was just saying words. The other people were doing actual sins,
right, you know, burning a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, whatever. It's pretty
funny like it says like that he said, ah, I can do
it even better. I was really waiting for something more drastic. Anyway,
אמרו לו, amaru lo, they said to him, והלא כסף וזהב שלו
הוא? velo kesef vezahav shelo hu? What do you mean, well we
have gold and gold we don't need God? Gold belongs to God,
שנאמר, she'ne'emar, לי הכסף ולי הזהב נאם ה' צבאות. Li hakesef veli
hazahav ne'um Hashem Tzeva'ot. אמר להם, Amar lahem, כבר נתנו לנו, kvar
natnu lanu, yeah, but it's ours, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, השמים שמים לה' והארץ
נתן לבני אדם. Hashamayim shamayim l'Hashem veha'aretz natan livnei adam. All
right,
I don't know, so he's just saying like what is the point?
The point is that he's completely rejecting that he doesn't need God
and these other kings weren't doing the same implicitly? I don't understand,
like, I'm a little still struggling with like what the message here
is, right, because at the end of the day these are just
words and presumably it was implicit or and even exhibited through actions
by the others, but maybe it is a difference, you know, about
it's better to be in a fighting relationship than in no relationship
at all, right? You know, so it's like, you know, at least
if they were doing it להכעיס, lehachis, you know, there's the old
point I think I've told you this thing like before, it's like,
you know, I I won't tell you the whole joke because we
don't have time but, but you know, להכעיס lehachis means like you
are in a relationship with God but you're doing it to spite
God. Whole, whatever, there's a joke about a whole guy becomes an
אפיקורוס Apikoros or whatever, somebody goes to visit him and he's like
doing everything, keeping all the מצוות, mitzvot, right? And whatever, why do
you do this? Well, you know, this is the way I'm used
to dressing. Why do you do this? Well, this gives meaning to
my life. Why do you do this? For you know, if you
don't believe, why are you doing it? He has an answer for
everything. So at the end the guy says to him, okay, like
I understand why you're doing everything, you've explained it all, but like
but I don't understand. You're still an אפיקורוס, Apikoros, so like why
don't you just like like do one עבירה להכעיס? aveira lehachis? So
the guy says, להכעיס מי? Lehachis mi? Right? So
so you know so like so maybe like that's the point. Like
all these other kings, they were doing the worst thing possible but
they were doing it because they were in a relationship with God.
But he was sort of like like trying to break off the
whole relationship. I so maybe that's the message. Yeah.
It sounds like שממית Samamith is a gecko. A gecko is...
what's a gecko?
It's a type of lizard.
But
what
where do you see...
what what are you seeing? שממית. Samamith. Where do we have שממית?
Samamith? It's what אמון Amon sacrificed.
Do we have that? Yes. Where
where do we have that? I don't do we get to this?
Oh, when it says העלה שממית, he'la Samamith, oh, as opposed to
cobwebs. Oh, that's interesting. A sacrificed salamander. That's interesting. Okay fine. All
right, let's finish up
here. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי, Amar lei Rava l'Rabba bar
Mari, מפני מה לא מנו את יהויקים? mipnei ma lo manu et
Yehoyakim? Now why if יהויקים was so evil and it was right
before the end of the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
so that was really his evil that ultimately tipped the scale, I
presumably why wasn't he on the list? Okay, משום דכתיב ביה, mishum
dich'tiv bei, because it says by him, ויתר דברי
יהויקים ותועבותיו אשר עשה והנמצא עליו. V'yeter divrei Yehoyakim v'to'avotav asher asa
v'hanimtzah alav. And
his abominations אשר עשה asher asa and what was found on him.
So what was
meant, what was found on him? מאי והנמצא עליו? Mai v'hanimtzah alav?
רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, Rabbi Yochanan veRabbi Eliezer, חדא אמר שחקק שם
עבודה זרה על אמתו chada amar shechakak shem avodah zarah al amato
to show how much his lust and his desire for his עבודה
זרה avodah zarah he had it like tattooed on, you know, on
his penis. וחדא אמר שחקק שם שמים על אמתו. v'chada amar shechakak
shem shamayim al amato.
God's name was there to show how much he despised it. Anyway,
says on him like on his manhood as it were. Anyway, so
the point is he was so evil why isn't he in... אמר
ליה: Amar lei: במלכים לא שמעתי. Bimlachim lo shamati.
I don't have any answer for the kings. There are some kings
that we should think would be on the list and they're not
on the list, right? We just spent this whole עמוד amud talking
about the evil of a lot of other kings who wasn't on
the list. So I don't know, I don't know why some kings
aren't on the list. But בהדיוטות שמעתי. behedyotot shamati. The list of
the non-kings, the, you know, the non-royal people who are on the
list, there was only four. You could, you could put a lot
of other people on that list too. There I've heard explanation why
some people who you would think should be on the list are
not on it. Okay, let's see what the explanation is. מכדי מאן
לא מנו את מיכה? Michdei maan lo manu et Michah? How about
מיכה, Michah, right? The one who brought the idol and whatever, you
know, in the early part of the history. So we mentioned him
before. Why isn't he on the list? מפני שפיתו מצויה לעוברי דרכים.
Mipnei shepito metzuya l'ovrei drachim.
Because even with all of his evil to God, whatever, he was
still good to people and he was always had bread available for
passersby. שנאמר כל עובר ושב אל הלוים. Shene'emar kol over v'shav el
ha'Leviyim.
Anybody that would come and go by the Levites. So in the
context of his פסל ועבודה זרה, pesel v'avodah zarah, but means that
he would be a welcoming presence. Okay, ועבר בים צרה. V'avar bayam
tzarah. Now we're gonna have a little דרשה about מיכה. Michah. ועבר
בים צרה. V'avar bayam tzarah.
So again, the word עובר over and עבר. avar.
And צרה tzarah remember that צרה tzarah is also the competing wife,
the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, passed through the ocean והכה בים גלים
v'hikah bayam galim and he smote with the waves the ocean. אמר
רבי יוחנן זה פסלו של מיכה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan zeh peslo shel
Michah. This is the פסל pesel of מיכה Michah because the דרשה
basically is that he was bringing the עבודה זרה avodah zarah out
of מצרים. Mitzrayim. So he was passing through the ocean. He was
in the generation of Egypt, you know, according to this story. Remember
there was also a story that he was saved from being built
into some of the buildings that they were building in Egypt and
so on. And he brought his עבודה זרה avodah zarah with him
through the split sea. Okay,
so,
and where were we, okay. ועבר בים צרה זה פסלו
של מיכה. V'avar bayam tzarah zeh peslo shel Michah. Where are we?
Okay. תניא רבי נתן אומר: Tanya Rabbi Natan omer: מגרב לשילה, Migerev
l'Shiloh, from גרב Gerev which is where מיכה Michah had his like
idolatry to שילה Shiloh which is where the משכן Mishkan was, is
ג' מילין, gimel milin, is three mil. Okay, three, like three miles.
והיה עשן המערכה, V'hayah ashan hama'aracha, it was
very close. His competing with the base, well, with the משכן, Mishkan,
but whatever, you know, the temple of God was, you know, they
were in very close locations. Three mil is not a lot. Three
mil you can is basically like three miles, okay. So, a little
less I think. Anyway, והיה עשן המערכה ועשן פסל מיכה מתערבים זה
בזה. V'hayah ashan hama'aracha v'ashan pesel Michah mitarvim zeh b'zeh.
And the smoke of the two of them, of the משכן Mishkan
and of the temple of מיכה's Michah idol, they were so close
that their smokes would mix, which obviously would be again showing like
this competing, you know, directly with God. ביקשו מלאכי השרת לדוחפו. Bikshu
malachei hasharet l'dochfo.
They wanted to push מיכה Michah away, like to totally destroy מיכה.
Michah. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא הניחו לו. Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch
Hu hanichu lo. No, leave him, שפיתו מצויה לעוברי דרכים. shepito metzuya
l'ovrei drachim. He makes his bread available to passersby. Right, so it's
really interesting, right, the counterbalancing. And before we had the counterbalancing, like
the תורה Torah, didn't counterbalance, right? These people were great תלמידי חכמים,
talmidei chachamim, that didn't counterbalance. Some of the things that counterbalanced, one,
well, one was like, you know, because he, you know, it says
that he made by מנשה, he's made his, he supported תלמידי חכמים.
talmidei chachamim. You know, not his own תורה, Torah. but he supported
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim or he protected the תורה. Or, you know,
and here it said he's like good for, you know, his הכנסת
אורחים hachnasat orchim and עוברי דרכים. ovrei drachim. ועל דבר זה נענש
אנשי פילגש בגבעה. V'al davar zeh ne'enash anshei Pilegesh b'Giva.
And it was because of מיכה's Michah sin that the people of
פילגש בגבעה Pilegesh b'Giva were punished. It's I think the same location.
אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא בכבודי לא מחיתם ועל כבודו של בשר
ודם מחיתם? Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu bichvodi lo mechitem v'al kvodo
shel basar vadam mechitem? You're coming to defend the honor of this
person who was wronged in the whole פילגש בגבעה Pilegesh b'Giva type
of a story, but you didn't defend my honor when the פסל
של מיכה pesel shel Michah was erected, you know, here in your
locale. And that's why they were punished. Okay, we will end with
this and we are all caught up. Okay, back.